Think about the last time you ate a bowl of rice.
You didn't wonder who grew it.
Almost no one does.
Here's the number that changed how I think about that.
In America, the average farmer is 58 years old.
More than 40% are over 65.
In Thailand,
where rice paddies once passed from parent to child like a birthright,
the story is the same.
The land is aging, the children left.
So who grows the food next?
The answer starts with math.
Farming costs years,
years of weather that doesn't cooperate,
yields that don't arrive,
seasons you gamble on and lose.
And the income?
It arrives by harvest,
not by paycheck, not on time.
A young person who moves from a Thai village to Bangkok can earn dramatically more in a year,
not because cities are better,
because a paycheck is something you can point to.
A failed harvest is something you absorb alone.
But the math isn't the whole story.
Even if the income was fair,
there's something else, an invisible tax.
In Thailand and across most of Southeast Asia,
the farm is where you came from,
not where you're going.
Generations of parents who worked the soil sent their children to school with one unspoken prayer.
Please, not this.
Degrees meant desks,
desks meant something better.
There's no LinkedIn profile for organic farmer,
no performance review for growing food without chemicals.
The work that I do, the 5 AM wake-ups,
the soil under my fingernails,
the rows I walk before breakfast,
none of it shows in the metrics the modern world uses to measure a life.
We built a world that rewards what it can count and what you grow in the ground is very hard to count.
I am one of the people who stayed.
Every morning I walk our rows,
check the soil with my hands,
smell the moisture before the rows come into focus.
Then I come inside and open a laptop.
I'm teaching myself to code.
I'm building things with AI,
not because I want to leave the farm,
but because the farm is exactly where that kind of building belongs.
The farm taught me patience.
The code taught me precision.
It turns out those are the same skill.
So why don't young people want to farm?
Maybe the real question is,
what did we teach them to want instead?
We told them the numbers were wrong.
We told them the soil was beneath them.
We never told them that what grows in the ground can grow into something entirely new.
Someone grew that bowl of rice.
Someone who stayed when every signal told them to leave.
The bravest generation of farmers isn't the one that planted the past.
It's the one brave enough to plant something the world hasn't seen yet.